A Guide to the Records of the Farmers Mutual Fire Association, 1895-1979
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Farmers Mutual Fire Association Records, 1895-1979
Library of Virginia
38627
3.35 cubic feet (Boxes 1-7)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Martha G. DuBose, Frederick, Maryland, 23 October 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Farmers Mutual Fire Association of Chester, Virginia was originally incorporated under the laws of the Commonwealth of Virginia on 10 August 1895 as the Farmers Mutual Benefit Association of Virginia, and its offices were located in Richmond.
The Association was reorganized under and amended charter and by-laws on 24 February 1898, and the office was moved to Chester. George E. Robertson was the first president, and Charles N. Friend was elected general agent, secretary and treasurer, which offices he held until his death on 16 June 1919.
The company insured dwellings, churches, stores, public garages, mills, motels, public halls, barns, grain, hay, livestock, machinery, and farm implements. Originally, the Association issued perpetual policies, and assessments were made as losses occured. Later, the company adopted the plan of issuing one, three, and five year policies with assessments being made yearly in advance.
In 1952, the charter was again amended, and the name of the company was changed to the Farmers Mutual Fire Association. It operated state-wide, but its principal area of business was within ten counties surrounding Chesterfield. Its assets were liquidated in 1979.
Scope and Content Information
Records, 1895-1979, of the Farmers Mutual Fire Association of Chester, Virginia. Includes accounts and receipts, bank books, cancelled checks, charters and by-laws, correspondence, financial reports, minutes, distribution and receipt ledgers, and liquidation papers.
Organization
Organized into the following three series: Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files; Series II. Minutes; Series III. Ledgers.
Contents List
- Correspondence and Subject Files
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1897-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
  - Accounts and Receipts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Applications for Membership and Insurance, 1928, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bank Books - Bank of Powhatan (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bank Books - Bank of Virginia (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bank Books - Chesterfield County Book (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bank Books - First and Merchants National Bank (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bank Books - Petersburg Savings and American Trust Company (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bank Books - Petersburg Savings and Trust (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bank Books - Southern Bank and Trust (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bank Books - Blank Policies (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cancelled Checks (Box 1, Folder 25-33)
  - Charter and Bylaws (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Corporation Registration Fee Receipts (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1897-1914 (Box 2, Folder 3-16)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1959, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Financial Reports, 1920, 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Liquidation Papers, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Northern Neck Mutual Fire Association (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Promissory Notes (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Stock Certificates, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Minutes
  - Minute Book #1, 1895-1924 (Box 3)
  - Minute Book #2, 1925-1951 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1952-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1-13)
- Ledgers
  - Distributions, 1940-1948 (Box 4)
  - Distributions, 1949-1953 (Box 4)
  - Distributions, 1955-1962 (Box 4)
  - Distributions, 1963-1970 (Box 5)
  - Distributions, 1971-1976 (Box 5)
  - Receipts, 1943-1952 (Box 6)
  - Receipts, 1953-1960 (Box 6)
  - Receipts, 1961-1965 (Box 7)
  - Receipts, 1966-1970 (Box 7)
  - Receipts, 1971-1976 (Box 7)
  - Policyholder, 1962-1977 (Box 8)
  - Assets, Liabilities, Income, Losses, and Operating Expenses, 1976-1979 (Box 8)